+55 31 9 96434978 Belo Horizonte, Brazil **○** prezeck@gmail.com

# Paulo Rezeck

Software Engineer / Ph.D. Student

**Portfolio**: rezeck.github.io scholar.google.com.br/rezeck linkedin.com/in/rezeck

I am a highly **motivated computer scientist** interested in solving real-world problems and challenges involving disruptive technologies such as **artificial intelligence**, **machine learning**, **computer vision**, **and robotics**. As an **expert in robotics**, I had the opportunity to develop **skills at both software and hardware** levels, involving embedded systems, sensor networks, and mechanical and electrical design. I participated in several R&D projects for the industry, developing prototypes of **teleoperated robotic systems and algorithms for detecting and tracking objects and people**. Such experiences improved my interpersonal communication, organization, and leadership skills.

#### **EDUCATION**

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (PHD) IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

 $06/2019 - 10/2022^*$ 

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 🔤

UFMG is ranked as #1 Latin America CS program: http://csrankings.org/#/index?all&southamerica Research area: Swarm Robotics, Artificial Intelligence and Probabilistic Graph Models

Advisor: Prof. Luiz Chaimowicz

Thesis: A Stochastic Framework for Multi-Emergent Swarm Robotics Behaviors

- Robot swarm control using probabilistic modeling using ROS middleware;
- **Development of a simulation environment** for swarms of robots using Gazebo;
- Papers published and presented at the best robotics world conferences (ICRA/IROS/RAL/AURO).

MASTER OF SCIENCE (MSC) IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

08/2016 - 02/2019

Brazil 💿

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG) **Research area**: Robot Design and Robotic Swarm

Advisor: Prof. Luiz Chaimowicz

Master's Dissertation: HeRo: An Open Platform for Robotics Research and Education

- Low cost robot design and construction using Autodesk F360 and Eagle;
- MCU firmware implementation using C/Wiring language for embedded systems.
- Kinematic control, sensor fusion using Kalman filter, mapping, and localization;

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (BSC) IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

08/2010 - 07/2016

Brazil 💿

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Research area: Robot Design and Robotic Swarm

Advisor: Prof. Luiz Chaimowicz

**Bachelor's Dissertation**: Development of a Framework for Experiments with Robots Swarms.

- Practice with with embedded computer (Gumstick Overo) executing OS Yocto;
- Practice with firmware implementation and hardware protocol (I2C, SPI, UART);

INTERNSHIP IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

02/2014 - 09/2015

Germany ==

Eberhard Karls University of Tübingen **Program:** Science without Borders

Research area: Robot Control, SLAM and Robot Vision

- Experience in mobile robot control (ackerman robot) and robot vision and object identification;
- Practice with filtering and sensor fusion (LiDAR, Odometry);
- Experience in simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM);

#### **PROFESSIONAL & ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE**

Tech Leader / Digital Inspection of Industrial Painting Activities based on Computer Vision

08/2020 - 07/2022

Petrobras / Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 🔤

**Description:** Recognition of human actions during the industrial painting activity using deep learning approaches.

- Technical leader of a team specialized in robotics and machine learning;
- Experience with neural networks for real-time detection of human pose (OpenPose/AlphaPose/PoseNet);
- Experience with neural networks for real-time tracking of objects (Deep SORT);
- Experience in **container software architecture** (Docker);
- Linux process communication and algorithm optimization (C++/Python/IPC/Socket/CUDA);

ROBOTICS ENGINEER / ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE ROBOTIC RACING

02/2019 - 04/2020

XQuad Team

Brazil 💽 / USA 💻

**Description:** Worked with a team specialized in UAV to create an AI for racing drones that can beat a human pilot. Awarded 7th/424 place at the Artificial Intelligence Robotic Racing (AIRR) competition:

- Worked with a team specialized in UAV to create an AI for racing drones that can beat a human pilot;
- Experience in Linux embedded system and algorithm optimization (C++/CMake);
- Experience with visual odometry (ORBSLAM2/ROVIO/VINS) and object detection algorithms (YOLO/OpenCV);
- Awarded 7th/424 place at the Artificial Intelligence Robotic Racing (AIRR) competition.

Student Researcher / Advanced Teleoperation of Excavators in the Mining Industry

10/2017 - 08/2020

Vale Institute of Technology (ITV) / Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 📀

**Description:** Develop a framework for excavator teleoperation using haptic technologies and visual immersion.

- Modeling/Construction of robotic excavator prototype using off-the-shelf parts and 3D printing;
- Robotic manipulator haptic control (C++/ROS/MOVEit);
- Construction/Control of a robotic head-like device for tele-immersion (C++/OpenCV/ROS);
- Development of a master/slave systems for teleoperation (Unity/WebRTC/ROS);

STUDENT RESEARCHER/ COOPERATIVE MAGNETIC-MAPPING USING SMALL UAVS

09/2015 - 08/2017

Vale Institute of Technology (ITV) / Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Brazil 📀

**Description:** Control of multiple drones creating a magnetic mapping for planning the ore deposits exploration.

- Experience in piloting and control drones;
- Experience with Linux embedded systems, image creation, and kernel compiling;
- Implementation of a visual interface for real-time control of drones (Python/JavaScript/QT);
- Implementation of applications for custom data acquisition and signal processing (Android Studio/Java/C++);

• English (proficient) • German (limited working proficiency) • Portuguese (native speaker)

## OTHER PROFESSIONAL QUALIficationS

Operating Systems	Practical experience with <b>Linux</b> ; integrated peripherals; conceptual understanding of sysfs, udev and dbus; controlling and automating LINUX processes using shell script; etc.
Linux Network	Intermediate skills: <b>networking tools</b> , routing packets, networking diagnostic procedures, and firewalls configuration under Linux environments.
Programming	Python, C, C++, Java, MATLAB. Experience with <b>embedded devices and optimized program-ming</b> . Experience with good programming practices, clean code, debugging, and testing;
Developer Practice	Experience with version control software ( <b>Git</b> /SVN), agile software development ( <b>Scrum</b> framework) and project report writing; UI design ( <b>Qt</b> ) and mobile ( <b>Android Studio</b> );
Hardware	Practice with C/Wiring microcontroller programming, especially <b>Arduino</b> , <b>ESP8266/ESP32</b> and PIC; hardware protocol (I2C, SPI, UART); <b>Circuit design and Assembly</b> ;
Robotics	Mechanical and electrical design (Autodesk Fusion/Eagle), control, motion planning, path planning and cooperative robots. Extensive knowledge of ROS/ROS2. Robot Simulation (Gazebo). Computer vision for robotics using (OpenCV), pattern recognition. Deep learning and deep reinforcement learning for robotics (TensorFlow/Open AI Gym).
Teaching Assistant	Mobile Robotics (2018) & Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (2021) both at UFMG.

#### SELECTED MEDIA APPEARANCES

- By Wevolver, 2022. Article: "HeRo 2.0, an ultra-low cost 3D-printed robotics platform, could open swarm robotics experimentation up to all". Language: English. Link: https://www.wevolver.com/article/hero-20-an-ultra-low-cost-3d-printed-robotics-platform-could-open-swarm-robotics-experimentation-up-to-all
- By G1/Globo newspaper, 2019. Article: "UFMG researchers participate in autonomous drone competition (Pesquisadores da UFMG participam de competição com drones sem piloto)". Language: Portuguese. Link: https://g1.globo.com/mg/minas-gerais/noticia/2019/07/04/pesquisadores-da-ufmg-participam-de-competicao-com-drones-sem-piloto.ghtml
- By O Tempo newspaper, 2019. Article: "UFMG Team is finalist at an AI competition in the USA (Equipe da UFMG é finalista em competição de inteligência artificial nos EUA)". Language: Portuguese. Link: https://www.otempo.com.br/interessa/equipe-daufmg-e-finalista-em-competicao-de-inteligencia-artificial-nos-eua-1.2201181

Journal: 7 + 1 (accepted, and under review)

Conference: 12

Workshop/Abstracts: 4

#### **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS:**

- Rezeck, P. and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). Chemistry-Inspired Pattern Formation with Robotic Swarms. In 2022 IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters and IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (RAL/IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.
- Rezeck, P., Azpurua, H., Correa, M. F., and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). HeRo 2.0: A Low-Cost Robot for Swarm Robotics Research (pre print). In 2022 Autonomous Robots Journal (AURO).
- Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, September). Cooperative Object Transportation using Gibbs Random Fields. In 2021 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.
- Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, May). Flocking-segregative swarming behaviors using Gibbs random fields. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) (pp. 8757-8763). IEEE.

#### JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS:

- (J1) Rezeck, P. and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). Chemistry-Inspired Pattern Formation with Robotic Swarms. In 2022 IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters and IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (RAL/IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.
- (J2) Rezeck, P., Azpurua, H., Correa, M. F., and Chaimowicz, L. (2022). HeRo 2.0: A Low-Cost Robot for Swarm Robotics Research (pre print). In 2022 Autonomous Robots Journal (AURO).
- (J3) Rezende, A., Miranda, V. R., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Azpúrua, H., Santos, E. R., Gonçalves, V. M., ... & Freitas, G. M. (2021). **An integrated solution for an autonomous drone racing in indoor environments**. Intelligent Service Robotics, 14(5), 641-661.
- (J4) Pires, A. G., Rezeck, P. A., Chaves, R. A., Macharet, D. G., & Chaimowicz, L. (2021). Cooperative Localization and Mapping with Robotic Swarms. Journal of Intelligent & Robotic Systems, 102(2), 1-23.
- (J5) Santos, V. G., Pires, A. G., Alitappeh, R. J., Rezeck, P. A., Pimenta, L. C., Macharet, D. G., & Chaimowicz, L. (2020). Spatial segregative behaviors in robotic swarms using differential potentials. Swarm Intelligence, 14(4), 259-284.
- (J6) Santos, E. R., Azpurua, H., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Corrêa, M. F., Vieira, M. A., Freitas, G. M., & Macharet, D. G. (2020). **Localization using ultra wideband and IEEE 802.15. 4 radios with nonlinear bayesian filters: a comparative study**. Journal of Intelligent & Robotic Systems, 99(3), 571-587.
- (J7) Azpúrua, H., Potje, G. A., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Freitas, G. M., Uzeda Garcia, L. G., Nascimento, E. R., ... & Campos, M. F. (2019). **Cooperative digital magnetic-elevation maps by small autonomous aerial robots**. Journal of Field Robotics, 36(8), 1378-1398.
- (J8) Macharet, D. G., Perez-Imaz, H. I., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Potje, G. A., Benyosef, L. C., Wiermann, A., ... & Campos, M. F. (2016). **Autonomous aeromagnetic surveys using a fluxgate magnetometer**. Sensors, 16(12), 2169.

#### **CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS:**

• (C1) Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, September). Cooperative Object Transportation using Gibbs Random Fields. In 2021 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) (pp. 9131-9138). IEEE.

- (C2) Rezeck, P., Assunção, R. M., and Chaimowicz, L. (2021, May). Flocking-segregative swarming behaviors using Gibbs random fields. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) (pp. 8757-8763). IEEE.
- (C3) Carvalho, L., Rezeck, P., Lima, M. V., Pinto, L., Freitas, G., Nascimento, E. R., ... & Campos, M. F. (2020, August). On the evaluation of force feedback augmented teleoperation of excavator-like mobile manipulators. In 2020 IEEE 16th International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE) (pp. 1401-1407). IEEE.
- (C4) Chaves, R., Rezeck, P., & Chaimowicz, L. (2019, December). **SwarMap: Occupancy grid mapping with a robotic swarm**. In 2019 19th International Conference on Advanced Robotics (ICAR) (pp. 727-732). IEEE.
- (C5) de Lima, M. V., Cid, A., Cadar, F., Pinto, L., **Rezeck, P.**, Grabe, T., ... & Campos, M. F. **Realimentação de Força para Teleoperação de Escavadeiras**. In 2019 14th Simpósio Brasileiro de Automação Inteligente (SBAI).
- (C6) E. R. S. Santos, H. Azpurua, P. A. F. Rezeck, M. F. S. Corrêa, G. M. Freitas and D. G. Macharet, Global Localization of Mobile Robots Using Local Position Estimation in a Geo Tagged Wireless Node Sensor Network, 2018 Latin American Robotic Symposium, 2018 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) and 2018 Workshop on Robotics in Education (WRE), 2018, pp. 39-44, doi: 10.1109/LARS/SBR/WRE.2018.00017.
- (C7) Rezeck, P., Frade, B., Soares, J., Pinto, L., Cadar, F., Azpurua, H., ... & Campos, M. F. (2018, November). Framework for haptic teleoperation of a remote robotic arm device. In 2018 Latin American Robotic Symposium, 2018 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) and 2018 Workshop on Robotics in Education (WRE) (pp. 170-175). IEEE.
- (C8) Rezeck, P., Cadar, F., Soares, J., Frade, B., Pinto, L., Azpurua, H., ... & Campos, M. F. M. (2018, November). An immersion enhancing robotic head-like device for teleoperation. In 2018 Latin American Robotic Symposium, 2018 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) and 2018 Workshop on Robotics in Education (WRE) (pp. 164-169). IEEE.
- (C9) Rezeck, P. A., Azpurua, H., & Chaimowicz, L. (2017, November). HeRo: An open platform for robotics research and education. In 2017 Latin American Robotics Symposium (LARS) and 2017 Brazilian Symposium on Robotics (SBR) (pp. 1-6). IEEE.
- (C10) Edwards, V., Rezeck, P., Chaimowicz, L., & Hsieh, M. A. (2016, October). Segregation of heterogeneous robotics swarms via convex optimization. In Dynamic Systems and Control Conference (Vol. 50695, p. V001T03A001). American Society of Mechanical Engineers.
- (C11) Perez-Imaz, H. I., **Rezeck, P. A.**, Macharet, D. G., & Campos, M. F. (2016, August). **Multi-robot 3D coverage path planning for first responders teams**. In 2016 IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE) (pp. 1374-1379). IEEE.
- (C12) Rezeck, P. A., Vieira, M. A., Chaimowicz, L., & Campos, M. F. (2013, October). On the development of a robotic system for telepresence. In 2013 Latin American Robotics Symposium and Competition (pp. 8-13). IEEE.

### ABSTRACTS, POSTERS AND WORKSHOPS:

- (W1) Paulo Rezeck, Héctor Azpúrua, Mauricio Ferrari & Luiz Chaimowics. "HeRo: An Open Robot Platform for Swarm Robotics Research". Robot Swarms in the Real World From Design to Deployment (Workshop at ICRA 2021), 2021, Xi'an China.
- (W2) Azpurua, H. **Rezeck, P.**, Torre, M., Zanetti, E. Freitas, G., Garcia, L., Nascimento, E. R., Macharet, Douglas G., Campos, M. F. M. "**Detection Of Uncrushables In Ore Piles Using Small And Autonomous Aerial Robots**". In: Mines Of The Future 2018, 2018, Aachen. Aims 2018,
- (W3) Rezeck, P., Azpurua, H., Chaimowicz, L. "Hero: An Open Platform For Robotics Research And Education". In: IEEE/RSJ International Conference On Intelligent Robots And Systems (IROS), 2017.
- (W4) Azpurua, H. Potje, G., Rezeck, P., Macharet, D. G., Freitas, G., Garcia, L., Campos, M. F. M. "Towards a Cooperative Method For 3D Magnetic Maps Generation Using Small And Autonomous Aerial Robots". In: IEEE/RSJ International Conference On Intelligent Robots And Systems (IROS), 2017.